Today's דף daf is פ״ט Peh Tet and we pick up at
the very top, first line of פ״ט ע״א, Peh Tet Amud Aleph,
and the discussion here is the following:
there's a ברייתא Baraita that said five people, five different groups brought
five different קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and then the skins of them
got mixed up, and one of them was discovered to have a
מום Mum on it and you don't know whose. So what do
you do? So assuming according to the way the גמרא Gemara modifies
it, this happens after the blood was thrown, so that definitely at
the time the blood was thrown, they were four of them were
fit to be eaten,
then those four were יוצא, Yotzei, you have to now you don't
know whose is whose so you have to burn it all, and
nobody brings a פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. So the גמרא Gemara says,
what do you mean nobody brings a פסח שני? Pesach Sheni? Four
of them don't have to, one does. It says yeah, but which
one? You don't know whose, so you don't know what to do.
So the גמרא Gemara says, well why don't you know what to
do? Let everybody bring their own they can't all be in a
group together because then you have people that are not part of
the group. So let them each bring a פסח שני Pesach Sheni
and make a תנאי Tenai and basically say, if I'm חייב Chayav
a פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, if mine was the one with the
מום, Mum, this is a פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, and if not,
let this be your שלמים, Shelamim, and everybody will eat it and
שלום על ישראל. Shalom Al Yisrael. So it says no, if it's
a שלמים, Shelamim, you have to give the חזה ושוק, Chazeh V'shok,
the breast and the side to the כהן. Kohen. And so, okay,
so give it to the כהן, Kohen, play it safe. Maybe it's
a פסח, Pesach, maybe it's a שלמים, Shelamim, give him that part.
Ah, but if it's a פסח, Pesach, then the כהן Kohen is
eating from the פסח Pesach that he is not part of. So
you can't again, you can't do this because you can't go ahead
and
properly deal with the חזה ושוק. Chazeh V'shok. So the גמרא Gemara
is not done. Let's take a look where the גמרא Gemara what
the גמרא Gemara says. So מי איכא חזה ושוק דכהנים הוא דאכלי
ליה, Mi Ika Chazeh V'shok Dekohanim Hu Deachli Leh, that
that's for the כהנים. Kohanim. So you can't just play it safe
and treat it either as a פסח Pesach or as a שלמים.
Shelamim. So says the גמרא, Gemara, ונייתי כל חד וחד כהן בהדיה,
Veneyti Kol Chad Vechad Kohen Bahadeih, let everybody who is each one
of these five guys bring a כהן Kohen with it and have
the כהן Kohen part of the ones that eat from their פסח.
Pesach. So the גמרא Gemara says, what what are you talking about?
Let's figure this out again. האי כהן היכי דמי? Hai Kohen Heichi
Dami? What's the story with this כהן Kohen you want each one
of them to have come with them? אי דעביד פסח, Ei Deavid
Pesach, if he's already brought his פסח Pesach on פסח ראשון, Pesach
Rishon, so דילמא היי פסח הוא, Dilma Hai Pesach Hu, we're back
to square one. Maybe this that your group is bringing isn't a
שלמים Shelamim or that you're bringing isn't a שלמים Shelamim but is
a פסח, Pesach, ונמצא פסח נאכל שלא למנוייו, Venimtza Pesach Ne'echal Shelo
Limnuyav, and the פסח Pesach is being eaten by somebody who is
not part of that group because he's not obligated in a
פסח
שני.
Pesach
Sheni.
Okay, I don't understand that, I don't understand the גמרא Gemara bring
a כהן Kohen for your פסח ראשון? Pesach Rishon?
No, you didn't bring a פסח ראשון. Pesach Rishon. You had to
burn all of your five פסחים, Pesachim, you didn't know whose had
the מום. Mum. Okay,
so now you're bringing a פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, פסח Pesach here
in this context means פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. You're bringing your פסח
שני Pesach Sheni because it might be obligated פסח שני, Pesach Sheni,
but it might not, so you're also backing it up and saying
maybe it's a שלמים, Shelamim, right?
You can't say כל הקבוע, Kol Hakavuah, like you can't no,
no, no, there's no קבוע, Kavuah, there's no קבוע. Kavuah. Anyway, so
it is you're doing it with the פסח Pesach but as a
backup it's a שלמים. Shelamim. Like you know, like your mama said
if you're going to be a rabbi, you should have a backup
job. Okay, so so if you're going to be a פסח שני,
Pesach Sheni, you should have a backup as a שלמים. Shelamim. Okay,
so it's a שלמים Shelamim as a backup. But if it's a
שלמים, Shelamim, then you have to give the חזה ושוק Chazeh V'shok
to the כהן. Kohen. All right, so have a כהן Kohen come
with you. But one minute, what do you mean have a כהן
Kohen come with you? You're back to the problem. If it's a
פסח Pesach and not a שלמים, Shelamim, then that כהן Kohen can't
be eating part of that. Ah, so make sure you have come
with you a כהן Kohen who's חייב Chayav in a פסח שני.
Pesach Sheni. But then you have the reverse problem, because if it's
a שלמים Shelamim and not a פסח, Pesach, then this כהן Kohen
who's חייב Chayav in a פסח שני Pesach Sheni is not being
יוצא Yotzei his obligation. Okay, so okay. So it says ואי דלא
עביד פסח, Vee Delo Avid Pesach, and if this I'm sorry, so
it says
wait a minute. ואי דלא עביד פסח, Vee Delo Avid Pesach, if
he didn't do a פסח, Pesach, his first פסח, Pesach, yeah here
פסח Pesach means פסח
ראשון, Pesach Rishon, I'm sorry, here he didn't do a פסח, Pesach,
so he's חייב Chayav in a פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, דילמא שלמים
הוא, Dilma Shelamim Hu,
and now it's a שלמים Shelamim and he's not doing his פסח
שני. Pesach Sheni. So what do you mean have the כהן Kohen
come? You got the same problem with the כהן, Kohen, that if
it's a פסח, Pesach, if the כהן Kohen is obligated פסח שני
Pesach Sheni maybe it's a שלמים, Shelamim, and if he's not obligated
in פסח שני Pesach Sheni maybe it's a פסח. Pesach.
So גמרא Gemara says ונייתי כל חמישה חד כהן. Veneyti Kol Chamisha
Chad Kohen. Wait wait wait, we got the
I got an idea. Let all of these five groups, five people
that are bringing their maybe פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, each one is
bringing a separate one, get one כהן Kohen with them who didn't
do פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, who's חייב Chayav in a פסח שני.
Pesach Sheni. So you have ראובן, שמעון, לוי, יהודה Reuven, Shimon, Levi,
Yehuda and יששכר, Yissachar, all bringing a separate קרבן, Korban, each one
of them brings something, five separate ones that might be a פסח
שני, Pesach Sheni, might be a שלמים. Shelamim. And one כהן, Kohen,
אהרן. Aharon. Okay, so this one כהן, Kohen, okay, he is going
to be, he's saying to ראובן, Reuven, if I, if you're the
one that's חייב Chayav in the פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, I'm part
of your group. And he says to שמעון, Shimon, if you're the
of your group. And he says the same to לוי, יהודה Levi,
Yehuda and יששכר. Yissachar. So and then this כהן Kohen each group
gives him the חזה ושוק. chazeh v'shoke. So he gets a nice
big steak meal, okay, a lot of חזה ושוק, chazeh v'shoke, okay,
and he eats all of them. So four שלמים Shlamims he's eating
and he's eating the חזה ושוק chazeh v'shoke of four שלמים Shlamims
which he's entitled to. And one, he's eating the חזה ושוק chazeh
v'shoke of a פסח, Pesach, which is his פסח שני. Pesach Sheni.
So we got all our bases covered.
Just doesn't know which one is which.
Just doesn't know which one is which, but he doesn't have to
know which one is which.
Like you're being part of different מינויות, minuyot, aren't you?
כפי שמיא K'pishmaya guys, only one of them is really a פסח.
Pesach. חד כהן דלא עבד פסח, Chad Kohen d'lo avad Pesach, נייתי
אינך חמשה, neiti inach chamisha, all five of them should get together
and get חד כהן דלא עבד פסח, chad Kohen d'lo avad Pesach,
one כהן Kohen that didn't bring the פסח. Pesach. דנימנויה D'nimnuye הני
חמשה פסחים, hanei chamisha Psachim, and
let let him and let let him be part of the group
of these five פסחים, Psachim, each one separately. דממה נפשך, D'mima nafshach,
either way you figure it, you work it out. איכא חד דלא
עבד פסח, Icha chad d'lo avad Pesach, one of these guys did
not bring a פסח Pesach and his קרבן korban is a פסח
שני. Pesach Sheni. And that one that he's eating from, this כהן
Kohen is being יוצא yotzei פסח שני Pesach Sheni דקא נפיק ביה.
d'ka nafik bei.
And the other four is a שלמים Shlamim and good, he's getting
the חזה ושוק chazeh v'shoke of a שלמים, Shlamim, good deal for
this כהן. Kohen. So the גמרא Gemara says so we got a
solution, so we still don't know why can't you everybody bring another
animal and be יוצא yotzei whoever needs the פסח שני Pesach Sheni
is being יוצא. yotzei. So the גמרא Gemara says
אלא משום דקא ממעט באכילת שלמים. Ella mishum d'ka mema'et b'achilat Shlamim.
No, the problem is going to be, you're right, this is perfect,
except that since, forget the כהן Kohen now, each guy brings this
animal and says this is either פסח Pesach or it's a backup,
it's a שלמים. Shlamim. But if it's a שלמים, Shlamim, if it's
a פסח, Pesach, how long do you have to eat it? A
day and the following night. Okay, or actually not even the following
night. You have a night. As it was pointed out, you don't
have the 14th, but anyway. Okay, but you have to eat it
by the morning. If it's a שלמים, Shlamim, how long you can
eat it? Yes, you get the rest of the day, you get
through the day of the 15th. So you're taking this lamb and
you're saying this is a פסח Pesach and if I don't, if
it doesn't have to be a פסח, Pesach, it's a שלמים. Shlamim.
But now you're going to have to make sure to eat it
by daybreak of the 15th, because it might be a פסח. Pesach.
What of all things? Well all five... no, if you're the כהן,
Kohen, but let's forget the כהן Kohen now.
You're just the owner, you're bringing this one lamb. So you still
have to eat a whole lamb, so anyway, okay. But you're bringing
this one lamb and you're saying this is a פסח Pesach and
if it's not a פסח, Pesach, it's a שלמים. Shlamim. But you
have to eat it by daybreak, okay, because it might be a
פסח. Pesach. But if it's a שלמים, Shlamim, you would have to
actually have, you'd have actually the whole next day to eat it.
So what you're going to do is, it might be a שלמים
Shlamim and you will therefore wind up
not being able to eat the meat of this שלמים Shlamim because
you'll stop eating by daybreak and you'll have to wind up burning
as נותר notar the meat of this thing because you won't have
finished it by daybreak and actually you'll have been in theory, you'll
be able, you should have been able to eat it because it
really turns out that it was a שלמים. Shlamim. Well, okay, but
one minute, okay. The גמרא Gemara says אלא משום דקא ממעט באכילת
שלמים. Ella mishum d'ka mema'et b'achilat Shlamim. You're limiting the time to
eat this if it really is a שלמים Shlamim and you think
it's a פסח. Pesach. דאילו פסח ליום ולילה, D'ilu Pesach l'yom valailah,
Pesach has a day and night, really just the night as we
pointed out before. ואילו שלמים לשני ימים ולילה אחד, V'ilu Shlamim l'shnei
yamim valailah echad, Shlamim has two days and one night. Okay, so
the question is going to be, okay, big deal look, it's better,
it's better than not bringing a פסח שני Pesach Sheni and you'll
just be careful and you'll eat it all. So we'll get back
to that in a minute. Let's finish the discussion because a lot
of these things sound like trivial concerns compared to the possibility that
you won't have brought your פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. So we'll get
to that in a minute. Let's finish up the גמרא. Gemara. The
גמרא Gemara wants to do everything perfect. So the גמרא Gemara says
okay, here. וניתי מותר הפסח. V'neiti motar ha-Pesach. ונימא, V'neima, one minute.
Bring a remnant of a קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. Which means, well
I'll say, I'll read the גמרא Gemara and then I'll say what
it means. ונימא, V'neima, אי דידי בעל מום אם מאי, ei didi
ba'al mum im mai, if my one back in ניסן Nissan was
the בעל מום, ba'al mum, האי דאייתי השתא ליהוי פסח, hai d'aiti
hashta lihavei Pesach, let this be the פסח, Pesach, פסח שני. Pesach
Sheni. אי דידי תם הוא, Ei didi tam hu, if the one
I brought back in ניסן Nissan was a תם, tam, ליהוי האי
דאייתי השתא שלמים דמותר פסח. lihavei hai d'aiti hashta Shlamim d'motar Pesach.
Let this be a שלמים, Shlamim, but a שלמים Shlamim coming
from the מותר פסח. motar Pesach. דנאכל ליום ולילה אחד. D'ne'echal l'yom
valailah echad. But it's a שלמים Shlamim that is derived from the
remnant of a פסח Pesach and that's eaten for a day and
a
following night. What does this idea mean? Let's say I set aside,
here's the simplest idea, I set aside a hundred bucks for my
lamb for the קרבן פסח korban Pesach and I sanctified this hundred
bucks. And in the end, I got it on sale and I
only spent eighty bucks for the lamb. So this twenty bucks is
sanctified with the קדושה kedusha of the קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. What
can I do with it? So we know what do you do
with anyway a פסח Pesach that is alive and you didn't bring
it on פסח, Pesach, you bring it after פסח Pesach as a
שלמים. Shlamim. So when I use this money to bring as a
שלמים, Shlamim, that's called a מותר פסח, motar Pesach, the remnant of
a פסח Pesach that is brought as a שלמים, Shlamim, but because
it originated in a פסח, Pesach, I only have a day and
a night to eat it. I don't have the full day. It
has the limits of the קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. So the גמרא's
Gemara saying I got a solution. You're bothered that you're going to
sanctify this animal and it might be a שלמים Shlamim and you'll
limit it, great. Here's what you do. You say either it's a
פסח Pesach and if it's not a פסח, Pesach, it should have
the קדושה kedusha not of a straight שלמים, Shlamim, it should have
the קדושה kedusha of a שלמים Shlamim derived from a פסח. Pesach.
And therefore from the very outset you're
Of course, it's a שלמים Shelamim. *Shelamim* based on a פסח Pesach,
*Pesach*. Of course the point is is that presumably the idea of
מותר פסח motar Pesach *motar Pesach* requires that it originated in a
פסח Pesach. *Pesach*. You can't initially sanctify something. I'm going to sanctify
this as leftover פסח Pesach *Pesach*. So that's what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* answers in the next line. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, וכי
מפרישים תחילה למותרות *vechi mafrishim techila lemotarot*? Can you initially set something
aside as leftovers? You can't cook leftovers. Okay? You can only have
leftovers. So you can't sanctify this as leftover פסח Pesach *Pesach*. So
you don't have that option. Now תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says, that's what
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says. תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafot* says, of course, that looks
like absurd. Nobody would have thought I can sanctify this as leftover.
So what תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says is, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* thinks what it means is the following, is that
I think I'm sanctifying this as a קרבן פסח korban Pesach, *Korban
Pesach*, and now that's it, period. Now if it turns out I
don't need a קרבן פסח korban Pesach. *Korban Pesach*, so this becomes
an animal sanctified as a קרבן korban, פסח Pesach *Korban Pesach*, which
is no, it's not פסח Pesach, *Pesach*, and I don't need it
as a פסח Pesach, *Pesach*, so it automatically has the status of
מותר פסח motar Pesach, *motar Pesach*. You understand the point? תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot*, it wasn't a stipulation. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* was just saying, just
sanctify it as a פסח Pesach *Pesach*. And then if it turns
out you don't need it as a פסח Pesach *Pesach* because you
already were יוצא yotzei, *yotzei* in ניסן *Nissan*, so then it's a
מותר motar פסח Pesach. *motar Pesach*. Okay?
The more fundamental problem is what's the likelihood of these five guys
to have that particular situation?
No, what do you mean? But they all five of them have
to bring now in אייר *Iyar* because they don't know
that they had a מותר motar *motar*.
No, no. So according to רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, you just said, I'm
sanctifying this פסח Pesach *Pesach*, and if not as פסח pesach *Pesach*,
I'm sanctifying it as מותר פסח pesach *motar Pesach*. And the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says you can't sanctify as מותר פסח Pesach *motar Pesach*.
תוספות *Tosafot* says, forget it. You say you're sanctifying it as a
פסח Pesach *Pesach* be-, now, if it turned out that you didn't
need to bring it because you were יוצא yotzei *yotzei* in ניסן
*Nissan*, what's the status of this animal that you sanctified as a
פסח Pesach *Pesach*? It's a מותר פסח Pesach *motar Pesach*. Okay. You
don't need to stipulate.
It's just the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is stipulating reality.
Just
right, just say I'm sanctifying it as a פסח Pesach? *Pesach*. If
it turns out you don't need a פסח Pesach, *Pesach*, it becomes
a מותר פסח Pesach, *motar Pesach*. So the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* answer
is yeah, that would work, but you shouldn't do it לכתחילה Lichatchila
*lechatchila*. לכתחילה lichatchila? *Lechatchila*, you have the-, you shouldn't sanctify something and
it might wind up that it's not needed and it's automatically leftover.
It would be better to stipulate either פסח Pesach *Pesach* or שלמים
Shelamim *Shelamim*, although if you had just said פסח Pesach *Pesach*, and
then the reality was you didn't need it and it had a
status of מותר פסח Pesach *motar Pesach*, it actually would have been
perfect. But you shouldn't do it לכתחילה lichatchila *lechatchila*. In the end,
the question's got to be, forget about לכתחילה lichatchila? *lechatchila*, this is
already בדיעבד bedi'avad *bedieved*. Right.
This whole situation is only to avoid burning the שלמים Shelamim, *Shelamim*
the day before you really need to burn the שלמים Shelamim, *Shelamim*.
Is there a problem burning מותר *motar* early?
Yeah,
it's considered like wasting meat of a קרבן korban, *Korban* that could
have been eaten. Of course the irony is that even when you
sanctify it as מותר פסח Pesach *motar Pesach*, you're still limiting the
time to eat it. It's just the reality is that you still
are preventing yourself from eating beyond daybreak. It's just in the one
case, you had the opportunity to and it was like squandering something
that could have been, whereas here you're already-,
there's a problem squandering the meat that could, right.
But here you're already sort of limiting it from the get-go. I
know it's funny that that was seen as an answer.
My suggestion yesterday was just like leave it over, you know, become-,
let it become מותר *motar* or something. I know I knew it
was sort
of a bit stupid, but it's still better than the alternative. All
right, so that's the ongoing question here. You have a lot of
לכתחילה lichatchila *lechatchila* concerns, but we're already in a בדיעבד bedi'avad *bedieved*
because the guy has to bring a פסח שני Pesach sheni. *Pesach
Sheni*. Okay, anyway, so let's go on. So that's what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is saying. No, you can't do this as making it
a שלמים Shelamim *Shelamim* or allowing it according to תוספות *Tosafot* to
be a מותר פסח *motar Pesach* because לכתחילה lichatchila *lechatchila* you're-, you
would limit the time or לכתחילה *lechatchila* you're not allowed to make
something into a מותר פסח *motar Pesach*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this. We're not done yet. וניטרחו ונייתי מותר פסח *uniterchu
unaiti motar Pesach*.
Oh, here's a solution. Five people, go-, put in a little effort
and-, and go ahead and make- and put in an ad in
the paper, Craigslist, and find people who have money left over from
their קרבן korban פסח *Korban Pesach* from ניסן *Nissan*. And say I
am in need of bringing a פסח שני sheni. *Pesach Sheni*, but
because of these crazy requirements, I have to bring it from מותר
פסח *motar Pesach* money. Does anybody have some מותר פסח *motar Pesach*
money or any animals that they separated for פסח *Pesach* and wound
up using another one and have a leftover animal? And I'm-, and
I'd be very interested in taking that over for you. And therefore,
you go ahead and you give me your מותר פסח *motar Pesach*
money, I give you some money in exchange, or you give me
your animal you would have- that you had separated off in-, in
ניסן *Nissan* but then you lost it, you brought another, so you
have this leftover פסח *Pesach*. I buy it from you. And this
animal I'll bring. So I'm not לכתחילה *lechatchila* making it מותר פסח
*motar Pesach*, it already is מותר פסח *motar Pesach*. And I'll bring
it and then I wind up bringing it either as a פסח
*Pesach* or as a שלמים shelamim *Shelamim*, and either way I eat
it and I get the כהן Kohane *Kohen* and I get him
to eat his part and שלום על ישראל *Shalom al Yisrael*. One
minute. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אלא *ella* fine, משום *mishum*,
here's the problem. You got me. You could wind up bringing the
animal, you get your כהן *Kohen* to eat it, you're safe. I
got another problem for you. משום סמיכה. Semicha, You have to do,
you have to put your hand on it if it's a שלמים.
shelamim, You have to do סמיכה, Semicha. rest your hands on it.
דאילו פסח לא בעי סמיכה De'ilu Pesach lo ba'i Semicha that you
don't need it for פסח, דאילו מותר בעי סמיכה de'ilu motar ba'i
semicha if it turns out it's a שלמים shelamim based on מותר
פסח you need סמיכה. Semicha Now the problem is, so what? So
do סמיכה Semicha even though you don't need it. But the גמרא
Gemara says in this famous discussion about women doing סמיכה Semicha and
so on, is that if you don't need it, then you're putting
your weight on an animal, on a קרבן, korban when you don't
need to, and it's like you're using קרבנות, korbanot, which is some
type of a rabbinic problem. Again, it seems like a very trivial
problem. So anyway, you shouldn't wind up doing סמיכה Semicha if it's
a פסח. So the גמרא Gemara says I got another answer. התינח
אנשים, Hataynach anashim, fine, if it's קרבנות אנשים, korbanot anashim, fine. If
it's men that have to bring this קרבן, korban I got, you're
stuck, because you'll have to do סמיכה Semicha. and if it's a
פסח you shouldn't be doing
סמיכה. Semicha. בקורבן נשים מאי איכא למימר, Bekorban nashim mai ika lemeimar,
let's say it's women that have to bring this as a, this
thing. They were the five people that got their things mixed up.
So then, if it's a woman's שלמים, Shelamim women don't have to
do סמיכה. Semicha הלכה למשה מסיני? Halacha le'Moshe mi'Sinai? Okay, that's a
separate thing but you're not required. Okay, and whether what type of
סמיכה Semicha, you do, okay, but you're not required. So it's perfect.
If it's a פסח it's good, if it's not a פסח it's
a שלמים, Shelamim and if it's a woman bringing it, so she
doesn't have to do סמיכה, Semicha so you're able to bring it.
You got it done. One minute. So let's see where the גמרא
Gemara goes with it.
אלא משום מתנות. Ella mishum matanot. Oh, here's the problem. You got
me. You got a way to bring it, מותר פסח, you're not
limiting the time to eat it, women, you're not, you're not getting
a סמיכה Semicha, problem, but what are you going to do with
the blood? I was waiting for that. What are you going to
do with the blood? דאילו פסח מתנה אחת. De'ilu Pesach matana achat.
If it's a פסח, you only put it on one corner of
the מזבח mizbeach or the wall of the מזבח. mizbeach. ואילו שלמים
שתיים שהן ארבע. Ve'ilu shelamim shtayim she'hein arba. And if it's a
שלמים you put it on
two diagonal corners that each corner it hits and it gets on
two walls. So the גמרא Gemara. says מאי נפקא מינה? Mai nafka
mina? Who cares? What difference does it make? והתנן, Ve'hatnan, we have
a principle, the משנה Mishna teaches כל הניתנים על מזבח החיצון שנתן
מתנה אחת כיפר, kol hanitanim al mizbeach hachitzon shenatan matana achat kiper,
that בדיעבד Bedi'avad any one application of blood, what, you know, בדיעבד
bedi'avad you're יוצא, yotzei. it suffices. So do the one thing and
you'll be יוצא yotzei whatever it is. אלא משום דאילו פסח בשפיכה.
Ella mishum de'ilu Pesach bishfika. No no no. Here's the problem. Even
if one application would be enough, we don't know how to do
that application. The פסח, it says דם זבחך ישפך, dam zivchacha yishafeich,
you pour it against the wall. ואילו שלמים בזריקה, Ve'ilu shelamim bizrika,
and by שלמים you throw the blood against the wall. So the
גמרא Gemara still says מאי נפקא מינה? Mai nafka mina? Big deal.
והתניא, Ve'hatanya, we taught in a ברייתא, beraita, כל הניתנים בזריקה שנתנה
בשפיכה יצא. kol hanitanim bizrika shenatanah bishfika yatza. Anything that should have
been thrown on the wall that was poured on the wall you're
יוצא. yotzei So you have a way to do this. So the
גמרא Gemara says no. אימור דאמרינן, Eimur de'amrinan, when could you do
any of this stuff? בדיעבד bedi'avad, you could do this, בדיעבד bedi'avad
you could do that, you could do אי עבד, ee avad,
that's if you already did it. By the way, it's important to
note that the word בדיעבד, bedi'avad, right, which means post facto, is
a conjunction of two Aramaic words: דאי עבד. de'ee avad. If, דאי,
de'ee, עבד avad you had already done it. Post facto. Okay. That's
if you already do the זריקה zerika that way, בדיעבד it's good.
לכתחילה נמי? Lichatchila nami? לכתחילה should we allow you to do it
this way לכתחילה? So again you have all of these לכתחילה concerns.
You're limiting the time, סמיכה, Semicha, this, that, but the point is,
why does it want everything to be perfect לכתחילה? נעבעך, Nebech, if
because of you one of these guys is not bringing his, is
not being,
no, for them we're יוצא yotzei in the first time, but one
of them is being per-, is being, is not being allowed to
do what's and you don't know which one, but one of them
is not going to be able to have been brought his קרבן
korban, פסח, פסח ראשון Pesach rishon or שני. So תוספות asks this
question. If you look at תוספות, תוספות says like this: הני מילי
בדיעבד, Hani milei bedi'avad, והוא הדין דכולהו אמרינן הכי, ve'hu hadin de'kulehu
amrinan hachi, אשמיכה ומתנות ונותר, a'semicha u'matanot u'notar, right, all of these
things we could have given this answer. Sure, you know, you know,
those things will work בדיעבד, but לכתחילה who wants it to work?
Now תוספות says ותימא וכי בשביל שמא יהיה נותר nosar, או משום
סמיכה semicha. דלא מעכבא או lo יעשו מתנה כהלכתן יתבטלו מידי ספק
כרת? sofek kares Big deal! Big deal! You got all these little
problems: oh you're going to limit the time, oh you'll wind up
doing סמיכה, semicha. the דם dam will be wrong. This guy is
going to be חייב כרת chayav kareth if he doesn't bring it!
So the גמרא Gemara says, so תוספות says ויש לומר דטוב שידחה
ספק כרת בשב ואל תעשה, ve'yesh lomar detov sheyidache safek kareth beshev
ve'al ta'aseh, better to passively let that happen, ממה שיעשו רובן שלא
כהוגן. mima sheya'asu ruban shelo kehogen. כי כבר רובם עשו פסח. Ki
kvar rubam asu Pesach. It's sort of like an אומרים לאדם חטא
כדי שיזכה חברך. omrim le'adam chata k'dei she'yizke chaverecha. If it was
just you, we'd say for you that would be the right tradeoff,
do one of these things לכתחילה wrong and make sure you're being
יוצא your פסח שני. But we're now having to tell four out
of five people to do these wrong things in order to ensure
that one person is being able to bring his קרבן korban, correctly,
so we don't say that. And at the end of the day
you assume that God is going to forgive him if he doesn't
have a choice and we won't let him do it. He's like
an אנוס oness anyway. But at least תוספות raises that as the
obvious question. Yes, Charlie. Wait, Charlie had his hand up. Preference to
people with their hands up. Yes.
The issue of the, the מותר money,
if if I
have מותר money.
That's an interesting question because you certainly couldn't use the קרבן korban?
for that because then it would be an עברה שנה. avra shana.
Can you use the money if you hold it over for a
year? Maybe. I'd have to check, I don't know, it's a good
question.
Second, the thing about the women, that's going to be a problem
because one of the people in the group we said before has
to be a priest. Oh, but
no,
but
that's not a problem. The priest is just one of the participants,
but would having the priest as, no, ממנפשך. mimanach. If it's a
שלמים, then the priest isn't part of the group and then it's
only the woman's קרבן korban and then you don't do סמיכה. If
it's the פסח and the priest is part of the group, then
you're not doing סמיכה. So, oh, that's a good question. Okay. Anyway,
but the meat of the שלמים anyway is נאכל nechal to also
to the whole to women from the כהן families regardless. So it's,
so you didn't, but regardless
it wasn't a question. Okay, Dov, you had a question?
I don't understand what it says there, what it means by you're
דוחה doche the ספק כרת sofek kares by not doing anything. Meaning,
everybody
is
דוחה שידחה ספק, doche sheyidche sofek, meaning you allow ספק כרת sofek
kares. to occur, you override the concerns of ספק כרת.
sofek kares You allow the ספק כרת sofek kares.
to occur, right, you override those concerns, right, the concerns of ספק
כרת. Okay. Next משנה. mishna. האומר לבניו, Ha'omer lebanav, somebody who says
to his children, sons, maybe but actually we'll see in a minute
what it says about the case of daughters.
הריני שוחט את הפסח על מי שיעלה מכם ראשון לירושלים. Hareini shocheit
et hapesach al mi sheya'ale mikem rishon l'Yerushalayim. I'm slaughtering the פסח
and this will be for
whoever gets to ירושלים Yerushalayim first, and he's trying to get all
his kids to get to ירושלים Yerushalayim in time for פסח. So
he and then he goes ahead and he slaughters it. כיוון שהכניס
הראשון ראשו ורובו, Keivan shehichni'as harishon rosho verubo, so presumably it sounds
like he's about to slaughter. So the guy comes in after it
was already
slaughtered. כיוון שהכניס הראשון ראשו ורובו זכה בחלקו. Keivan shehichni'as harishon rosho
verubo zachah bechelko. First guy, what's defined as getting there first? ראשו
ורובו, rosho verubo, like סוכה, sukka, ראשו ורובו בסוכה. rosho verubo basukka.
So as soon as the first person so a race, he got
it by a nose, not enough to get it by a nose,
right? You have to be ראשו ורובו rosho verubo in, that guy
was first and that's the one that satisfied wait a minute, that's
the one that
satisfied the condition and therefore it turns out retroactively he was the
one that was part of the קרבן korban, פסח. Fine, so first
of all that assumes יש ברירה, yeish breira, which has been an
ongoing question in these משניות. mishnayot. He already slaughtered it and it
sounds like afterwards it can be determined who was included. But then
the משנה mishna goes on and makes another point, that זכה בחלקו
ומזכה את אחיו עמו. zachah bechelko umezakeh et echav imo. After the
first guy gets it, the first son, he can have his brothers
join in with his portion. Okay, now that's a little bizarre because
they weren't included in the שחיטה shechita and what's anyway the mechanism
for him being ומזכה את אחיו עמו? mezakeh echav imo? So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. שמע מינה יש ברירה, Shma mina
yeish breira, like the גמרא Gemara asks by all these משניות, mishnayot,
which all these משניות mishnayot do seem to hold יש ברירה, yeish
breira, that something can be determined later and retroactively it'll be determined
that you were part of the group. So the גמרא Gemara is
always trying to get out of it. So here's how it gets
out of it. אמר רבי יוחנן כדי לזרזן במצוות קאמר. Amar Rabbi
Yochanan kedei lezarezan bemitzvot kamar. Yeah, it wasn't he didn't really mean
it. He was just trying to get them to be eager and
to be running after מצוות. mitzvot. In the end, the father had
in mind and when he slaughtered it, it would be for all
the kids. He was just telling them this to get them to
work harder. Okay, so there's really no ברירה breira and what not,
he really had them all in mind anyway. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says דיקא נמי דקתני, dika nami dektani, it can also be
inferred from the משנה mishna because the משנה mishna teaches ומזכה את
אחיו עמו, umezakeh et echav imo, that the brother who wins gets
his other brothers now to be part of together with him. So
how does that work? אי אמרת בשלמא דאמינהו מעיקרא, Iy amarta bishlama
de'aminhu meikara, if the father had always intended for all the brothers
to be part of it, so שפיר, shapir, it works. אלא אי
אמרת דלא אמינהו מעיקרא, Ela iy amarta d'lo aminhu meikara, if he
had never really originally designated them, it was only the one who
was going to get there first and retroactively that would be the
one, so you understand how that one works out, it was ברירה
breira in the whole thing, but how do the others come on
board? לבתר דשחט מי קמימנו? Labatar deshachit mi kamimnu?
After he slaughtered it, how could the other ones join in? Like
this one guy, that was the ברירה, breira, but how do the
other ones work out? דהתנן Dehatnan we taught and this is literally
the next משנה. mishna. נמנין ומושכין ידיהן ממנו עד שישחט, Nimnin u'moshchin
yedeihen mimenu ad sheyishacheit, you can withdraw and join in until it's
slaughtered, but there's no mechanism for the brothers to join in after
it was already slaughtered. So שמע מינה, shma mina, so therefore that
is a good proof, you see that this whole thing actually was
all he doesn't mean it. Or now of course the point is
and what's the whole point of the משנה? mishna? The point of
the משנה mishna presumably is that that's how we will choose הלכתית
halachically to interpret his words. הלכתית, Halachically, you know, which is always
the good question, right? If he says this type of a thing
and this goes back again to the issue of the assumption that
children, even adult children and wives and Jewish slaves are, you know,
they can be counted with the פסח as long as they don't
protest. Right? Remember the way the גמרא Gemara interpreted earlier they don't
have to
verbally acquiesce. but they're assumed to be part as long as they
don't protest. So presumably what this משנה mishna. *Mishna* is teaching is
that when but as long as the father who's שחט shachat. *shechting*
it or the husband has them in mind. So if this משנה
mishna. *Mishna* is teaching is when the father makes this type of
stipulation, we're going to interpret it as if he really wanted really
everybody to be part of it. Of course you wonder, what's say
everybody shows up in ירושלים *Yerushalayim* after nightfall? Would he have wanted
them to be part even in that case? Did it require at
least one of them got there? Anyway, but that's how we're interpreting
what he's saying, that he does not really mean to stipulate, he
really wants them all to be part of it. תניא נמי הכי
Tanya nami hachi *Tanya nami hachi*, we thought similarly. לעולם *Leolam* מעשה
וקדמו בנות לבנים *maase vekadmu banot lebanim*. There's a case where the
daughters actually got to ירושלים *Yerushalayim* before the sons. And ונמצאו בנות
זריזות ובנים שפלים *venimtzu banot zrizot ubanim shfelim*.
It turns out that the daughters was the ones that were eager
and zealous, and it was the boys who were lazy, the sons
who were lazy. Now the חידוש chidush *chiddush* is, the point is
that it doesn't say נמצאו בנות אוכלות ובנים אינם אוכלים *nimtzu banot
ochlot ubanim einam ochlim*, right? It seems like the only relevance to
this is who gets the prize of being the זריז *zariz*. So
you see, it's not a real stipulation, it's all just to encourage
them to be זריז *zariz*. Yes, Dov?
עבד כנעני *Eved Knaani* is also included, no?
עבד כנעני *Eved Knaani* is also... yeah, it would definitely be included.
But presumably, right, I mean, yeah. Right, right. But that's even against
his protest, that's automatically a member of the household. These have to
more have some degree of acquiescence and so on. But it's all
to get them to be eager. In the end, it really didn't
matter. Okay. Reminds me, I don't know why where my head's go
about this, this was a great thing. I remember, actually don't remember
where I read this, I think it was like in one of
these...
anyway like Reader's Digest, you know that they used to have these...
I still get them at the at the barbershop. They used to
have these like little, you know, Only in America jokes or whatever.
So this mother is saying, so this daughter is adult daughters complaining
to her mother she can't get her kids to clean up the
house. She says, you know, I got a great idea for you.
Here's what you should do. Take some quarters, hide them in various
places along the house, and then when they clean up, if they
do a good job, they'll find the quarters, and that'll be a
good incentive for them to do a good job cleaning up. So
the girl says... so the daughter says, oh that's a great idea,
she says. Why did you never do this with us? I did!
All
right, so anyway, so נמצאו בנות זריזות ובנים שפלים *nimtzu banot zrizot
ubanim shfelim*. All right, so now, anyway, so next משנה mishna? *Mishna*.
אומר *Omer*... לעולם נמנין עליו עד שיש בו כזית kezayit, לכל אחד
ואחד *Leolam nimnin alav ad sheyesh bo kezayit lechol echad ve'echad*. So
you can keep on adding people until, you know, the lower limit
is that it has to be a minimum כזית kezayis *kezayit* for
every person part of the group. But up to that you can
add as many people as possible. נמנין ומושכין ידיהן ממנו עד שישחט
*Nimnin umoshchin yedeihen mimenu ad sheyishachat*, what we just talked before, you
can keep on joining and withdrawing your membership until it's שחט shachat
*shechted*. Again, never tells us exactly the process of joining. Is it
verbal, do you have to give money, it seems very loose exactly
how that is defined and kept track of. You can do it
until the moment of שחיטה shechita *shechita*. רבי שמעון אומר עד שיזרק
הדם ad sheyizarek hadam *Rabbi Shimon omer ad sheyizarek hadam*. No, you
can change things until the blood is thrown, which is surprising. We'll
see in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* a qualification on this. So here's
what the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says. מאי קמ''ל *Mai kamashma lan*? What's
the חידוש chidush *chiddush*? Keep on joining until there's a כזית *kezayit*,
maybe that's obvious. הא קמ''ל *Ha kamashma lan*, here's the חידוש *chiddush*.
דאע''ג דמינו עליו חבורה chabura? זו *de'af al gav demimnu alav chavura
zu*, I mean, what's the חידוש *chiddush* maybe that you can add
and withdraw until it's שחט shachted. *shechted*? So the חידוש *chiddush* is,
even if one full חבורה chabura, *chavura* counted on it, חוזר ונמנין
עליו חבורה chabura אחרת *chozer venimnin alav chavura acheret*. The entire חבורה
chabura, *chavura* can be removed and replaced with another חבורה *chavura*. Again,
the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't spell out the חידוש *chiddush*, but we'll find
out later that there's an opinion that you need one of the
original members of the group to remain on. You cannot completely have
it as a complete new group. So the גמרא *Gemara* is saying
this משנה Mishnah: *Mishna* is saying not that way. This משנה Mishnah,
*Mishna* is saying you could completely change over the membership as long
as you did it before it was שחט *shechted*. It could be
completely new members than the original members. Okay. נמנין ומושכין ידיהן עד
שישחט *Nimnin umoshchin yedeihen ad sheyishachat*. And then רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*
says you can even change it once it's... until the זריקה zrika.
*zarika*. אמר אביי מחלוקת לימשך *Amar Abaye machloket limashech*. The dispute is
to when can you withdraw, that רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* allows you
to withdraw prior to the זריקת הדם zrikas hadam. *zerikat hadam*. Okay.
דרבנן סברי מחיותיה דשה *Derabbanan savri michiyotai deseh*, right? It says, ואם
ימעט הבית מהיות משה *ve'im yimat habayit mehiyot miseh*. So the rabbinic
read of that is not if it turns out that there's very
few people, it says אם ימעט הבית *im yimat habayit*, if you
want to reduce the number of the בית bayit *bayit*, which now
means חבורה *chavura*. You want to reduce the בית *bayit*, you can
do that מהיות משה *mehiyot miseh* as long as it's still a
שה *seh*, as long as it's still a sheep, right? מחיותיה דשה
*michiyotia deseh*, while the sheep is still alive. That's what the rabbis
say. Okay. ורבי שמעון סבר מהויה דשה *VeRabbi Shimon savar mehavaya deseh*.
And until it is sort of becomes a שה *seh*, meaning until
its its its act of being sacrificed is complete. So until the
דם *dam* is thrown you can still withdraw your membership. Until you're
יוצא *yotzei* the קרבן korban *korban*, which you understand the logic of
that, right? Because as long as the קרבן korban. *korban* doesn't have
the blood thrown, it's not yet... brought as a קרבן and you
can back out. And then he bring the אימורים. emurim. That's about
backing out, one minute. אבל Aval למנות lemanos but to join in,
דברי הכל divrei hakol עד שחיטה ad shechita that you have to
do before שחיטה shechita which makes sense. If you want to be
a part, you have to be a part of it from the
beginning of the process. If you want to withdraw, says רב שמעון,
Rav Shimon, you can withdraw anytime before the end of the process.
Okay, no, and then you join in with another group that didn't
שחט. דאמר קרא De'amar Kra there, but even there רב שמעון Rav
Shimon agrees you have to join from the beginning before the שחיטה
shechita. because the פסוק pasuk says במכסת נפשות bemichsas nefashos
according to the number of souls והדר תכוסו vehadar tachosu and תכוסו
tachosu here is read by חז"ל Chazal not as you should number
like מכסה michsa but תכוסו tachosu from the Aramaic word of כסס
ksas means שחיטה. shechita So according to the number you should שחט
and whole emphasis of being שוחט-ing shochet למינויו liminuyav שלא למינויו shelo
liminuyav so you have to be if you want to be part
of the group you have to be there before at the moment
of שחיטה shechita counted in, but you can withdraw according to רב
שמעון Rav Shimon before זריקה. zrika. תניא נמי nami, הכי we saw
similarly in a ברייתא, beraisa, נמנין ומושכין ידיהם ממנו עד שישחט nimnin
umoshchin yedeihem mimeno ad sheyishachat you can change membership until it's שחט.
רב שמעון אומר Rav Shimon omer נמנין עד שישחט nimnin ad sheyishachat
no you can join and that has to be before שחיטה shechita.
ומושכין עד שיזרק הדם umoshchin ad sheyizarek hadam
you can withdraw anytime before זריקה. Okay. Just wait, I'm sorry, before
we go on, why, if
he's saying that if it involves that עבודה avoda then why not
extend it to the other? The other four
עבודות. avodos.
First of all, as I said, logically if you want to be
part of it you have to be part of everything, right?
And number two is the פסוק. pasuk. פסוק pasuk says תכוסו איש
במכסת נפשות תכוסו tachosu ish bemichsas nefashos tachosu so that's read as
פשט pshat of the פסוק. pasuk. Okay, now let's see the next
משנה.
Mishnah But as he said, he says עד שיזרק הדם ad sheyizarek
hadam.
to withdraw, not to join.
Right, no, why, yeah, he's saying that תכוסו tachosu is שחיטה. He's
saying you can join until later, עד שיזרק הדם. ad sheyizarek hadam.
Because if you're not part of the whole thing you're not part
of it.
Right, so why can't he withdraw until עבודה avoda is complete?
In other words, עד שיזרק הדם. So עבודה avoda is complete, it's
זריקת הדם. You're יוצא the קרבן, anything else is not מעכב. meakev.
Okay, let's take a look. Next משנה. הממנה עמו אחר בחלקו. Hamemaneh
imo acher bechelko.
Now again, this is again this whole fuzziness of how do we
get to be who joins in the group. Okay, so so you
know, I'm in this group with a couple of my friends and
then I go ahead and you know, I see Charlie over there
and Charlie's walking around looking for a group and it says, "You
know what Charlie, come join us. You'll be with us." And I
didn't bother consulting the rest of the group. Okay, so what's the
הלכה? halacha? רשאין בני חבורה ליתן לו את שלו Rashain bnei chabura
liten lo es shelo והוא אוכל משלו והן אוכלין משלהן. vehu ochel
mishelo vehein ochlin mishelahen. So I go back to the group and
inform them, "Hey guess what? I invited Charlie to eat with us."
They said, "Okay, that's very nice. Until now there were five of
us, now you brought in the sixth, you take a fifth of
the animal and
you go eat it with Charlie by yourself. Okay, we're not dividing
it six ways, only dividing five ways, you take your fifth,
you asked him without our permission, you two eat your one portion."
All right, and רש"י Rashi says the other point about this is
that we're even now really dividing, you know, it's not just that
we're sitting in a circle and we're cutting up and giving me
on my plate and I eat with Charlie, we're sending the two
of us away so that now we're dividing the פסח into two
חבורות. chaburos. You take your portion you guys go away, you can
eat your portion by yourselves, we're dividing what we have equally here.
Yes, דב? Dov?
Is this very wordy in this משנה? Why does it say רשאין
בני חבורה ליתן לו את שלו, rashain bnei chabura liten lo es
shelo, והוא אוכל משלו? vehu ochel mishelo? Why is it repeated?
I don't know. Yeah, I guess it's just making it clear that
ליתן לו, liten lo, yeah, I mean, yeah,
I don't know. I mean, it's true, I mean, again I think
that might be why רש"י Rashi emphasizes that they're really split up
into two separate groups because the sense of the end והוא אוכל
ואינו אוכל vehu ochel ve'eino ochel gets a sense of like they
really have fully separated off, not just a way of dividing the
meat. Maybe that's exactly where רש"י Rashi is getting it from.
Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. איבעיא להו. Ibayya lehu.
The question, they raised the question. בני חבורה שהיו ידיהם של אחד
מהן יפות. Bnei chabura shehayu yedeihem shel echad mehen yafos. So we
all started eating and it turned out that one of these guys
was gobbling it up much faster than everyone else, which we didn't
realize before we had joined in together. So the euphemism is you
have very nice hands. Okay, you're grabbing the stuff and eating it
much quicker than we can. מהו שיאמרו לו? Mahu sheyomru lo? So
once we realize that, can we say to him, טול חלקך וצא?
tol chelkecha utzei? Get your portion and leave. Okay, now so again
the question is did we already start eating, is that then a
problem, פסח נאכל בשני מקומות pesach ne'echal bishnei mekomos because we didn't
divide it up in the beginning? Again, the question is does צא
tzei really mean to break off as a separate חבורה? Okay, but
anyway somehow maybe when we were eating the חגיגה chagiga we realized
what a glutton he was, so now before the פסח comes along
we want to get you to separate off. According to רש"י that
says it's literally a separate חבורה, again based on this language of
צא. tzei. Just what? Give him his fair portion. You're not kicking
him out, you're giving his portion but no more, and say get
out of here because normally what it makes you realize is that
normally the way they would do it is they wouldn't be so,
you know, precise. They'd bring out the whole lamb, they'd set out
all the plates, and everybody would eat together, very nice, communal, whatever.
But in this scenario, maybe we have to divide up equal portions,
but again the language וצא ve-tze according to רשי actually means we're
not just giving equal portions, we're actually telling you, "You go away,
we don't trust you, you go eat your portion somewhere else," and
then we can eat it maybe equally and communally. Okay, so are
you allowed to do that or not? So מי אמרינן מצי אמר
להו הכא קבילתון, mi amrinan matzi amar lehu hacha kibeiltun,
maybe he can say to them, "Hey, what do you mean? You
guys accepted me as a member of the group and the understanding
was we all eat shared, so you can't now kick me out
of your group." או דילמא מצי למימר ליה, o dilma matzi lemeimar
leh, or maybe they could say to him, כי קבלינן ki kablinan
for what purpose did we accept you as our group? לתיקוני זבח
letikkunei zevach for the sake of the קרבן, meaning that it shouldn't
be נותר, that everybody would get their right portion. I mean, those
were our assumptions. אדעתא דתאכל טפי מינן
לא קבלינך, adaata detachal tefi minan lo kablinach, we didn't accept you
assuming that you were going to be so gluttonous and eat more
than your portion, so now we're able to say, "You go be
your own group." תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. הממנה אחרים
עמו בחלקו, hamemaneh acherim imo bechelko, our משנה: you went ahead and
you got other people to join with you, רשאין בני חבורה ליתן
לו את שלו והוא אוכל את שלו והן אוכלים את שלהם. rashain
bnei chabura litein lo et shelo vehu ochel et shelo vehein ochlim
et shelahem. Our משנה, we can give you your portion and say
goodbye if you asked somebody to join in with you. So מאי
טעמא, mai taama, what's the reason? לאו משום דהוה ליה כי ידו
שלכם אין יפות? lav mishum de-hava lei ki yadav shelachem ein yafot?
This is like you turned out to be a glutton. You came
to us and surprise, you now have a double appetite, okay, which
so and
so you see, somebody that has effectively a huge appetite we can
say get out of here. Now, of course, the difference is that
when I invited Charlie, I didn't ask the rest of the group,
so obviously the rest of the group could say, "We don't want
Charlie to be a part of it." It's less obvious that the
group can kick me out if they which they accepted willingly as
a group if they find out that I'm so gluttonous. So that
could have been an obvious distinction. Let's see what the גמרא's answer
is. And the גמרא if because the whole argument that they can't
kick me out is they agreed, they never agreed to Charlie.
So the גמרא ואי סלקא דעתך, ve-ee salka daatach, let's see what
the גמרא says with this, ואי סלקא דעתך ידו יפה מצי אמר
להו קבליתו, ve-ee salka daatach yado yafa matzi amar lehu kibeiltu,
but if in the case of one guy gluttonous he could say
tough luck, you guys already accepted, להוי האי כי ידו יפה, lehvei
hai ki yado yafa,
so let this guy be like he turned out to have a
huge appetite because he invited somebody else and they should be stuck.
So you see the fact they can't kick him away should show
you that they can I mean the fact they can't kick him
out shows you can kick out a guy with a huge appetite.
Again, big difference here is they never agreed to Charlie. But the
גמרא says another answer. אמרי לא, amri lo, no, it's not a
proof. דשאני, deshani,
two people is different than one person with a big appetite, even
forgetting that they never agreed to Charlie. Why is two people different?
דאמרי דאי נמי תרוייהו כחד מנאי חבורה הוא דאכלי, de-amri de-ee nami
tarvaihu kechad mnei chabura hu de-achlei, even if me and Charlie combined
only are very are very finicky eaters and we're only going to
eat combined the equivalent of one person, the reason they can kick
us out has nothing to do with the quantity that he'll eat.
The reason they're entitled to exactly, the reason they're entitled to kick
us out is they don't like Charlie or he's a stranger and
since when are we supposed to welcome people to eat our קרבן?
So
מצי אמרי ליה, matzi amri leh, they could say to him, דלא
ניחא לן איניש דגרוך גבן. delo nicha lan inish degaruch gaban. We
don't want any strange people or people amongst us. כל דחזינא ליה
ומרחמנא ליה יתיב ויכיל. kol dechazina leh umerachamana leh yativ ve-yeichol. Okay,
fine. So anyway, so the reason you can kick me out if
I go ahead and invited Charlie was because who's he? This isn't
the nice intimate group that we had picked, and it has nothing
to do with the idea of eat, of appetite. But if it
turns out that I have a big appetite, maybe they're stuck with
me and they can't kick me out. Dov, you had a question?
Why doesn't the משנה say, "Listen buddy, slow down"? The assumption is
they said that it didn't work.
"You can't tell me to slow down! I'm part of this group
and I'm entitled to eat as much
as I
want!"
So the גמרא approves of this. It's like the first time we've
seen that there's a social aspect to the grouping of, right, and
it sheds light on the idea of turning the face away and
אביזרי דכלה, avizrei de-challa, right, yeah,
where it's not appropriate to kind of turn away from your group
in the social sense unless there's some extenuating circumstances like the כלה
kallah which sheds light on on those right the
whole sense of בית and the coming together and the intimacy, yeah,
you're right, meaning it's not just like a business arrangement, all of
these things, the fact that it had to point out the idea
of the כלה kallah and the way it pointed out that they
just make separate groups by turning away points out that this is
right, excellent point, that this really is this social grouping and not
just a convenience an arrangement of convenience. Yes, yes, Rivka.
It seems to me this whole
thing belongs in Miss Manners. As long as everybody gets their כזית,
why are they trying to figure all this out?
Well, this is exactly what I'm saying, that there's apparently there's a
social aspect to it,
but the גמרא shouldn't be legislation.
But but there's also but
no,
but there's also there's also a financial element to it. Excuse me,
I paid... I paid a hundred dollars for my fifth of this
lamb, and I was expecting twenty lamb chops, and because of you,
I'm only getting five lamb chops. So there's a financial element, it's
not just a manners element.
Why is it not הלכה? halacha? It's הלכה. halacha. It's not maybe
הלכות קרבן פסח, Hilchos Korban Pesach, but it's הלכות דיני ממונות, Hilchos
Dinei Mamonos, right? I don't understand. I don't understand if we all
went into a restaurant and we decided we would split the bill
and there was an implicit understanding we're all going to order from
the middle of the menu, and you go ahead and you start
ordering ten of the most expensive dishes, right? And you say, well,
we agreed we're splitting the bill. You don't think there's a הלכה
halachic question there of whether... Since when is דיני ממונות Dinei Mamonos
not הלכה? halacha?
I am trusting you that that case could be brought to an
American court, right? Who has the financial responsibility? I don't understand why
just because there's a social dimension there isn't also a financial dimension
and it's not הלכה. halachic.
דרך ארץ Derech Eretz is important even when there's הלכה. halacha.
Well, that's also true. Okay, so let's keep on going. We're going
to see those interesting discussions which do sound a little more like
דרך ארץ Derech Eretz discussions. Okay, anyway, תא
שמע, Ta Shma, come in here. השמש שאכל כזית בשר, HaShamash she'achal
kezayis basar, remember this? Where you have the attendant who started, he
was roasting the פסח and he's...
תא שמע, Ta Shma, we
don't know, we're trying to prove it. Okay, you have the attendant...
Shhh... You have the attendant who's eating a...
who's roasting the פסח by the oven, and he's inadvertently, he's not
paying attention and he, or he's taking a little taste and he
ate a כזית of meat right there by the oven, בצד תנור.
betzad tannur. And now he can't eat his פסח in two places.
He can't join with the group in the other room that he
was supposed to be with. אם היה פיקח ממלא כריסו ממנו, Im
haya pikeach memalei kreiso mimenu, if he's smart, he should get his
fill, if he's an equal member of the group, let him get
his fill now, because he can't move his location. ואם רצו בני
חבורה לעשות טובה עמו, Ve'im ratzu bnei chaburah la'asos tovah imo, if
the people of the group wanted to be nice to him, בואין
ויושבין בצדו ואוכלין, bo'in ve'yoshvin betzido ve'ochlin, they come and they sit
next to him and that's where they'll have their group. דברי רבי
יהודה, Divrei Rebbi Yehuda, that's what רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says. So
רצו ratzu in, only if they want to be nice, yes, לא
רצו לא, lo ratzu lo, if they don't want to be nice,
then they're entitled to go to the other room. ואמאי, Ve'amai, why?
נימא להו, Neima lehu, הקבלתון. hakibaltun.
Let him say, what do you mean, we agreed to be a
group? So the same way you could say if that was an
argument to say you can't kick me out if I'm gluttonous, it
should be an argument to say you can't make me be eating
in a separate room and therefore you should be required to come
here. Of course there's an obvious difference. The גמרא says no, שאני
התם דאמרי ליה, shani hasam de'amri lei, there it's different that they
could say back to him, yeah, we accepted you as a group
and you accepted to be part of our group, but you went
ahead and you went off by yourself. כי קבלינך, Ki kablinach, under
what circumstances do we accept you as part of our group? אדעתא
דנשדרך קמן, Atat de'nishdrach kaman, you by the way anyway are a
שמש, shamash, you're the attendant, so we sort of maybe let you
be in our group in exchange for you, you know, being our
attendant during the meal. But there was understandings that you would come
to our service. למיטרח לן ולדידך, Limtrach lan u'ledidach, that we would
come to be ashlapped because of you? לא קבלינך, Lo kablinach, we
didn't accept you. And I would assume even if he wasn't a
שמש, shamash, the point could be, you know, you made a choice
to break off, we don't have to be dragged after you, as
opposed to the guy who's a glutton, that's just a reality of
who he is and he's not breaking off from the group, they're
trying to break him off. תא שמע, Ta Shma, come in here,
yeah.
Is it such a thing as sweat equity in this kind of
thing, that he's...?
It sounds like, that's a good phrase, right, it sounds like that's
what it sounded like, that they were letting him be part of
the group because he was doing the work, right.
Yeah, he shares something in exchange for work
but not for money.
תא שמע, Ta Shma, come in here, yeah. בני חבורה שידיו של
אחד מהן יפות, Bnei chaburah she'yadav shel echad mehen yafos, so we
got a ברייתא. braisa. It seems so funny, it seems like we
asked the question because we already knew the ברייתא, braisa, but we
just wanted to sort of build up the issues that were involved,
okay, but we have a ברייתא braisa that answers the question. It's
exactly this. בני חבורה שידיו של אחד מהן יפות, Bnei chaburah she'yadav
shel echad mehen yafos, I mean obviously we knew the ברייתא braisa
because even the euphemism is the same, right? You have the people
of the חבורה that one of them turned out to be a
real, a real, you know, פרעסער, fresser, a real, you know, glutton.
רשאים לומר, Resha'im lomar, they can tell him, תאכל חלקך בקצי, tuchal
chelkecha bekatzei, take your portion and get out of here, they can
kick him out. Okay, בלא עוד, belo od, but again, question about
פסח is נאכל בשני מקומות, ne'echal bishnei mekomos, etc., when do they
tell him this? But okay, בלא עוד אלא אפילו חמשה ועשו סיבולת,
belo od ela afilu chamisha ve'asu siboles, now here you get Rivka
to close to your phrase, it's again, it's a communal... You have
five purses, people that have learned סופות Suphos know about this idea
called
סיבלונות, siblonos, which is that basically people that would, you know, either
when any of our group gets married, we all take over handling
of a various set of meals or even without getting married, we
might have had actually somebody in the ישיבה yeshiva started this, I
never heard of such a thing, but it's called like this... what's
it called? The food חבורה, lunch-co-op, right? That everybody takes turns, ten
people, making the lunch for everybody else in the group and you're
on a rotation. So let's say we all did this, we all
chipped together to have some communal meal, and it turns out that
one guy is a big glutton. Okay, what's our right? So חמשה
שעשו מהן... אפילו חמשה ועשו סיבולת, chamisha she'asu mehen... afilu chamisha ve'asu
siboles, you people five people did this like communal meal, and one
guy turns out to be... and he's eating much more than his
share. So רשאים לומר לו טול חלקך וצא, reshayim lomar lo tel
chelkecha utzei, they can give him his portion and say, "Get out
of here, we're not eating it communally, certainly not with you." Okay,
everybody else will eat, you know, in a nice מענטשלעך menschlich communal
way, but you take your portion and get out of here. So
you see that even if they eat—that you don't assume that they
accepted a person's membership
regardless. They accepted his membership assuming he would eat within a normal
range of how everybody else eats.
It might even go the other way. Let's say they thought like,
"Oh, he doesn't eat anything," and he eats—oh, brother,
I don't think—I think—yeah, yeah, yeah. שמע מינה. shma mina. So okay,
it's a good point that you can kick somebody out of the
group, give them their portion if it turns out they're eating disproportionately.
So again,
Rivka, I don't agree. There's money involved. Okay, so מאי לאו, mai
lav, why is it a חידוש the case about the, about like
just the eating group? Why's that more of a חידוש than the
פסח? פסח, לא מיבעיא קאמר, lo mibaya ka'amar, it goes without saying.
לא מיבעיא lo mibaya פסח, it's even—it's more obvious by a פסח
they can kick the guy out, דמצי אמר ליה dematzi amar lei
that they can say to him, כי קבלינך לתיקוני זביחא. ki kablinach
letikkunei zvicha. We accepted you because, you know, the קרבן needed an
equal number of eaters and that was our primary motivation. Yes, there's
a social aspect, but our primary motivation was we needed a group
for the קרבן, and you're not part and you are disproportionate, you're
not what we expected, get out of here. It's not fundamentally about
the social
grouping. אלא אפילו סיבה, ela afilu sivoh, but even the case of
the group eating, which is fundamentally a social group, okay, נמי, דצוותא
בעלמא הוא, detzavta be'alma hu, it's only צוותא tzavta which is like
a getting together, it's only really about the social communal aspect, and
you might think he could say, "Look, fundamentally this isn't about eating,
right? Fundamentally it's about us getting together and having this communal experience,
and that's why we all accepted it, because we all wanted to
be part of it. So even if it winds up that I'm
eating more, right, our fundamental agreement was about the social grouping, and
you can't kick me out just because the food is disproportionate." Nevertheless,
no, רשאים לומר לו טול חלקך וצא, reshayim lomar lo tel chelkecha
utzei, even though it is about the social grouping, that also assumes
a roughly equal division of the food. And if he's being disproportionate,
they can kick him out of the group. Okay, איכא דאמרי, ika
de'amrei, some say הא לא מיבעיא לן, ha lo mibaya lan, none
of this was a question. It was always obvious you could kick
out somebody that ate disproportionate, you could kick him out of the
group. Okay, אלא הכי הוא דמיבעיא לן, ela hachi hu demibaya lan,
this was our question. בני חבורה רשאים לחלוק או אינם רשאים לחלוק?
bnei chavura reshayim lachalok o einam reshayim lachalok? Forget this section of
a disproportionate. What we want to know is סתם, stam, here we
have, we're all joined together, can't—do we have to eat it communally,
or can we say, "You know what? Let's divide up all the
portions," and, you know, and from the get-go either we'll be separate
חבורות, chavuros, again, not with any particular thing, it's not that anybody's
a פראסער. fresser. We just want to go ahead and divide it
up amongst everybody, or, you know, even if we're all, as I
think the way רש״י Rashi says it, or I would suggest we're
all sitting here, but we want to give each person—you know, it's
not buffet style, it's family style, each one gets their portion. I
have to tell you, I can identify with this because I like
to savor my food, but it's a real problem in a family
style—if you're eating it too slowly and savoring it, all the stuff
that's on the communal dish is all gone by the time you're
ready for your next bite. So can you go ahead and divide
it or not, without anybody being the פראסער? fresser? So רשאים טול
חלקך
וצא—so reshayim tel chelkecha utzei the גמרא says like this:
רשאים לחלוק או אינם? reshayim lachalok o einam? תא שמע, ta shema,
come and hear, בני חבורה שהיה אחד מהן ידן יפה, bnei chavura
shehaya echad mehen yadan yafa, we have this ברייתא, braisa, רשאים לומר
לו טול חלקך וצא. reshayim lomar lo tel chelkecha utzei. If one
of them is a bigger eater, they can kick him out. But
it says no, ידן יפה yadan yafa אין—it's in only because he's
a disproportionate eater. אין ידן יפה לא, ein yadan yafa lo, but
if he's not disproportionate and there's no particular justification for dividing, you
can't. שמע מינה, shma mina, that's a good proof. And according to
this, by the way, Rivka, your point of הלכה halacha is—is that
it's actually saying, according to רש״י Rashi it's saying you can't arbitrarily
make multiple חבורות, chavuros, but the way, you know, I would suggest
reading it is saying even if we all remain together, we're supposed
to, unless there's a good justifying reason, eat communally, eat from a
communal plate, which again sort of underscores the idea of having this
as a communal experience.
Yes, and it's—it actually codes this, it actually codified the הלכה halacha
in the רמב״ם Rambam and שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch.
For פסח or other things?
For—for both.
Okay, well we're about to get to the other thing, so let's
take a look. רב פפא ורב הונא—and Rav Pappa veRav Huna now
we get a lovely story. רב פפא ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע
Rav Pappa veRav Huna brei deRav Yehoshua אריבו ריפתא בהדי הדדי. arivu
rifta bahadi hadadei. They went ahead and they literally like did עירוב,
eruv, right, remember עירוב eruv is where you join in together with
a loaf of bread, so it's the same verb here. They joined
together with a loaf of bread. Okay, they decided to have a—to
have a meal together, okay, presumably it's not even literally פת. pas.
Okay, so what? Potluck. Okay, not exactly clear, but okay, maybe, maybe
they equally contributed food or they equally contributed money. אדאכל רב הונא
בריה דרב יהושע חד, adachal Rav Huna brei deRav Yehoshua chad, and
this is like again exactly my experience every day—not every day, but
whatever—when Rav Huna the son of Rav Yehoshua had had one portion,
אכל רב achal Rav So רב פפא *Rav Papa* had eaten four
portions!
Exactly, so he he knew, right?
He knew the idea. Now you gotta grab, you grab now, you're
not getting! Exactly, oh that's a good point, he said, right? He
knew, he knew fast, you gotta use your elbow. Okay, אמר ליה
*Amar Lei* so רב הונא *Rav Huna* said to him פלגי *Palgi*
get you know what? Give me my portion, I'll go eat by
myself. Okay, I don't like this communal eating. אמר ליה *Amar Lei*
or at least, you know, again, I don't know if he's going
off in a huff, but he wants his portion. He doesn't want
the communal, the communal eating. אמר ליה *Amar Lei* so רב פפא
*Rav Papa* said to him קביעתון *Kavietun* no, you accepted me as
part of your group, like the language used before. אייתי כל הני
תיובתא *Aitei kol hanei tyuvta* so he gave all these evidence that
you're allowed to ask for your portion and go and you know,
to give the guy his portion and go out or you ask
for your portion and you go out. ושני
כדשנינן *V'shani k'deshaninan* he gave all the answers. You know, no, that's
maybe different. That was the case with the שמש *shamash*. That was
the case that you had some new guy to join you. So
it's not necessarily here. Here it's the same two people and we're
not allowed to and you can't demand that we divide. So אייתי
בני חבורה *Aitei bnei chavurah*. Ah, then he asked him the last
ברייתא *braita* we had that explicitly said this case. That you have
an equal group by the קרבן פסח *korban Pesach* and one guy
turns out to be a פריסר *fresser*, you can give him his
portion. אמר ליה *Amar Lei* התם דאמרי ליה *hatam d'amrei lei*. Ah,
that's the פסח *Pesach*. That's because they can say כי קבלינך לדכוותיה
דזבחא *ki kavalnach ledichvutei dezivcha* we when did we accept you? To
the purpose of the sacrifice. That's because it was about the קרבן
*korban* purposes and it's not fundamentally a social group and therefore they
can kick him out, but this was just fundamentally about a social
grouping. Even if I wind up being a bigger eater, you can't
kick me out. It's not fundamentally about the food. So הגמרא *haGemara*
says אייתי סבולת *Aitei sibolet*. Ah, then he asked him the end
of the ברייתא *braita* that's specifically about a
social group, group of eating food, of getting together for a meal
and that if one is disproportionate you can kick him out. So
fine, okay, you proved your point. While they were having this discussion,
by the way, he ate another four portions. Okay, I'm kidding. פלגי
*Palgi* fine. He gave him his portion and they divided up. אזל
*Azal* so then רב הונא *Rav Huna* went with his portion and
ערב בהדי רבינא *Arav behadi Ravina* and he joined together with רבינא
*Ravina*. Okay, and he had he said, oh, I'll get somebody else
to join with me, I can't eat this whole thing by myself.
You wanted some whatever. Anyway, he joined together with רבינא *Ravina*. אדאכל
רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע חדא *Adachal Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua
chada* now with his new grouping, while he ate one portion, אכל
רבינא תמניא *achal Ravina tamnya*. So רבינא *Ravina* had eight portions! So
אמר *amar* he said מאה פפי ולא חדא רבינא *me'ah Papei v'lo
chada Ravina*. I'd rather have a hundred of רב פפא *Rav Papa*s
than one רבינא *Ravina*. Because a hundred of רב פפא *Rav Papa*s
is four hundred, so okay I guess it's an exaggeration. Somebody's going
to tell me how that math makes sense. Anyway, maybe he has
a hundred separate times with רב פפא *Rav Papa*.
And like let's say, you know, let's say I'm eating twice as
fast as you, but this other guy is eating half the fast
as everyone else in the group. Could you still say then you
can't kick me out because this guy just eats slower but between
the two of us...
That's a good question. I don't know. That's a good question. Good
question. תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*. Let's do let's get one more line
in. Okay. הממנה אחרים עמו על פסחו *Hamemaneh acherim imo al Pesacho*.
You go ahead and you have other people join you with your
פסח *Pesach*. ועל חגיגתו *v'al chagigato*. Or your חגיגה *chagigah*. Now חגיגה
*chagigah* also was eaten and everybody wanted to have a portion and
so on although that was more of a standard concept of שותפות
*shutafut* of a קרבן *korban* brought for שותפות *shutafut* as opposed to
פסח *Pesach* had a specific idea of like שה לבית אבות *seh
l'veit avot* and מנוייו *minuyav*. But anyway, either way, we're now dealing
not with the issue of חבורה *chavurah* as much as with the
issue of if the פסח *Pesach* is already sanctified and then somebody
joins the group, how does he get a portion in a קרבן
*korban* that's already been sanctified? That's the question here. And what does
he do with his money? And I already sanctified money. I've set
out a hundred dollars for my פסח *Pesach*. You came along and
you said oh come join us I already got a פסח *Pesach*.
So if your animal was חולין Chullin. *chulin*, it would be great,
right? I give you the money and in exchange I get a
portion of your קרבן *korban*, of your animal, and the קדושה *kedusha*
of that hundred dollars transfers to a portion of the קרבן *korban*.
Whatever, we'll worry about the exact mechanics but you can see how
it works. But let's say you already sanctified your animal. How do
I get a portion of it and what do I do with
my money that is sanctified? So that's what this ברייתא *braita* talks
about. Okay. הממנה אחרים עמו על פסחו *Hamemaneh acherim imo al Pesacho*
ועל חגיגתו *v'al chagigato* מעות שבידו חולין Chullin, *Ma'ot she'beyado chulin*. I
give you my money, my money becomes חולין *chulin* and I get
a portion in your קרבן *korban* even though everything's sanctified. Now הגמרא
*haGemara* is going to figure out tomorrow how those mechanics worked. והמוכר
עולתו ושלמיו *V'hamocher olato v'shalmav*. Now that's by a פסח *Pesach*, but
if I sanctified an animal as an עולה Olah. *olah* or a
שלמים *shlamim* and then I and then you said oh you got
an עולה Olah *olah*? I want to bring an עולה Olah *olah*.
Too late. I'm already the owner, you're not the owner, it's already
sanctified, you can't transfer ownership of a קרבן *korban*. לא עשה ולא
כלום *Lo asah v'lo klum*. You didn't do anything. So obviously the
juxtaposition raises the question. How do you transfer ownership or bring somebody
into your ownership of a פסח *Pesach* but by all other קרבנות
*korbanot* you can't transfer ownership? And that's exactly the difference that this
ברייתא *braita* is pointing out. ומעות קדש *U'ma'ot kodesh*. And whatever money
I gave to be part of your ownership as opposed to פסח
*Pesach* I could become part and the money becomes חולין *chulin*. And
here I try to buy your עולה. Number one, I don't get
to have it as mine. You can't transfer ownership of an עולה.
And the money that I gave, יפלו לנדבה, yiplu linidavah,
actually have to go ahead and be used to as a donation
to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash to bring to bring a קרבן
in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So we'll see why in the
גמרא. But it's the exact opposite. By a פסח I can join
in even after it's been sanctified. By an עולה and a שלמים
I can't. By a פסח the money becomes חולין. By an עולה
and שלמים the money, even if maybe even if it starts as
חולין, have to go for the purpose of a קרבן. Okay, and
we will pick up tomorrow to see how to make sense of
that whole piece.